<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<ns2:metadata
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0 http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0/onedcx_v1.0.xsd"
	xmlns="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:ns2="http://ns.dataone.org/metadata/schema/onedcx/v1.0"
	xmlns:ns3="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<ns2:simpleDc>
		<title>Mugs of the Mesa and Old Chocolate: Evidence of Prehistoric
			Cacao Use in the Mesa Verde Region of the North American Southwest
			(Contributed Poster)</title>
		<creator>De Loera, Alexia (The University of San Diego)</creator>
		<creator>Millar, Donald (The University of San Diego)</creator>
		<creator>Klein, Lauren (The University of San Diego)</creator>
		<creator>Fernandez, Andrew</creator>
		<subject>ceramic analysis</subject>
		<subject>Mesa Verde</subject>
		<subject>American Southwest</subject>
		<type>Document</type>
		<identifier>http://alpha.tdar.org/document/48701/mugs-of-the-mesa-and-old-chocolate-evidence-of-prehistoric-cacao-use-in-the-mesa-verde-region-of-the-north-american-southwest-contributed-poster
		</identifier>
		<type>Text</type>
		<contributor>Society of American Archaeology</contributor>
		<publisher>Society of American Archaeology, San Francisco, California
		</publisher>
		<type>conference</type>
	</ns2:simpleDc>
	<ns2:dcTerms>
		<abstract>Undergraduate Anthropology and Chemistry students at the
			University of San Diego (USD) collaborated on the application of
			analytical chemistry to archaeological ceramics. USD curates 1000’s
			of prehistoric Southwestern artifacts, all of which are available for
			student research. We examined some of the collections vessels for
			cacao, which is the raw form of chocolate. Patricia Crown and W.
			Jeffrey Hurst recently found it in cylinder jar fragments from Chaco
			Canyon. Crown’s methodology was adapted for our project, using the
			university’s mugs from the Mesa Verde region near Durango, Colorado.
			The chemical analysis of residues extracted from Pueblo II to Pueblo
			III period (A.D. 1100 to 1300) Mesa Verde mugs indicates the presence
			of theobromine, a chemical component of cacao. In all, 24 vessels
			were tested using liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry. Two mugs
			had positive indications for chocolate. Cacao is endemic to
			Mesoamerica and was used in ritual practice that made its way north
			with other exotica. The chemical results will be discussed along with
			an analysis of long distance trade networks as well as the
			morphological, iconographic and use-wear characteristic of each
			vessel.</abstract>
		<created xsi:type="W3CDTF">2015-04-02T21:49:28-07:00</created>
		<bibliographicCitation>Mugs of the Mesa and Old Chocolate: Evidence of
			Prehistoric Cacao Use in the Mesa Verde Region of the North American
			Southwest (Contributed Poster). Alexia De Loera, Donald Millar,
			Lauren Klein, Andrew Fernandez. Presented at Society of American
			Archaeology, San Francisco, California. 2015 ( tDAR id: 48701) ;
			doi:10.6067/XCV848701</bibliographicCitation>
		<spatial>North America - Southwest</spatial>
		<references>http://alpha.tdar.org/document/48701/mugs-of-the-mesa-and-old-chocolate-evidence-of-prehistoric-cacao-use-in-the-mesa-verde-region-of-the-north-american-southwest-contributed-poster
		</references>
		<spatial xsi:type="Box">northlimit=42.02554333723747;
			southlimit=30.675715404167743; westlimit=-115.5322265625;
			eastlimit=-102.36926193209942;</spatial>
		<!--  <temporal>2014</temporal> -->
		<temporal xsi:type="Period">start=2015;end=2016;</temporal>
		<created>2015</created>
	</ns2:dcTerms>
</ns2:metadata>